A Guide to the Papers of Ernest Hemingway, 1925-1961, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], [1926?] February 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:23)
    Hopes nothing bad has happened to him and that he was just in an Irish black mood. Proud he wrote The Undefeated. Will be in New York in one week. Really fond of [Robert] McAlman. Don't let any of them die of disease, but the more he thinks of it, any form of dying can be made pretty swell. He looks forward to it, but wants to be at least 85 when it happens. Life is pretty swell. 6250-a
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Herbert] Gorman, [1926 April 4], ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:24)
    Glad to get letter. Went to Bill Baird of the Three Mountain Press who promised to send him copy of The Cantos. Finished re-writing The Sun Also Rises, and having swell time in town. Has box for all week at 6-day bicycle race. Took all next month's rent and food money to buy it. Can sell extra four seats if he wants to. Scribner sent him proofs of satire. Hopes he will let him have one of the books of poems. Has seen no literary gents, but sees by clippings they are constant attendees at literary teas, i.e. Bercovici, Bromfield, Wharton, Seldes, etc. to write the local color stories. Will be in Spain middle of May on. He has got mixed up in making some bullfight films for South American and European consumption. Will get his bullfights free. Got tight when leaving New York. Paris is very exciting. Urges [Gorman] to come over. He is grown up and restful after New York. 6250-c
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Georgia] Lingafelt, 1927 October 3, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:25)
    His books have been Three Stories and Ten Poems (1923), In Our Time (1924)The Torrents of Spring(1926) The Sun Also Rises (1926), and Men Without Women (1927). If she ever gets any rare editions, he would appreciate hearing about it. If they became valuable, he might have something to leave his children. Lists number of copies printed and publishers. 6250-c
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Charles T.] Scott, 1929 January 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with 2 typed transcripts. (Box-folder 3:26)
    Remembers receiving other photograph, autographing and sending it back. Pleased to sign this one. Just finished long novel that he has been working on since last February, which is out next fall. Perhaps appearing as serial in Scribner's meantime. Includes signed photograph of Ernest Hemingway: "To Charles Thomas Scott with all best wishes..." See Photographs for original. 6250-c
  - Ernest Hemingway to Mr. Bridges, 1929 March 11, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:27)
    Sailing for Havana to Boulogne. Will be in Paris April 22. Returning the proofs with two omissions, which are necessary. Hemingway worked hard on the passages and has gone over and over it "in order that it might be printed without in anyway giving offense." Wishes that in the future cuts of the passages could be suggested on the proof and not on the manuscript. 6250-r
  - Ernest Hemingway to Mr. Gud, 1929 October 28, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:28)
    No plans for writing any differently, except always to try and write better. As for immortality, that's something we have to die to find out about. But [James] Joyce, for Dubliners and the end of Ulysses, is surest bet for it of anyone living. People writing as well as they can don't change their way of writing any easier than they can change their skins. 6250-a
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Paul] Romaine, 1932 January 15, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:29)
    He may reprint his poem. $10 - $15 would be all right for reprinting. Not in favor of his reprinting the "other Double Dealer piece." Reprinting already published fragments not in his racket. 6250-y
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Samuel] Putnam, [1932] June 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:30)
    Glad to serve on his jury. States the best three books he read in 1932 are 1919 by John Dos Passos, Conquistador by Archibald Macleish, and The American Jitters by Edmund Wilson. 6250-a
  - Ernest Hemingway to Paul Romaine, 1932 August 9, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l.; with envelope. (Box-folder 3:30a)
    Hemingway responds angrily to Romaine's suggestion to stop writing about "Lost Generations and bulls;" he could be jailed for the publication of his political beliefs; Dos Passos and Wilder are not good writers and he has not read Faulkner's "early crap." 6250-ab
  - Ernest Hemingway to M. E. Gilfond, 1934 November 17, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:31)
    Hemingway allows photograph of his house to be used in a postcard. 6250-k
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to [?] Armstrong, 1935 January 10, D, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:32)
    Telegram: "Arrived yesterday. Meeting Harrington Saturday." 6250-s
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Dick and Jane [Armstrong], 1935 February 5, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:33)
    Thanks Jane for swell typing job. It was a beautiful job figuring out what the hell Hemingway's holograph meant and he appreciates it. Max Perkins and Dos [John Dos Passos] have read it and like it very much. Hemingway is feeling better about it. Believes Jane likes it because she likes Africa and Dick likes it because he likes to drink. Asks them a favor: would they contact a few people in Cuba to help out with an article he is writing on Cuban marlin fishing? 6250-s
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Charles B.] Strauss, ALS photocopy, 2 pp. on 2 l. with photocopy of envelope (Box-folder 3:34)
    Doesn't know why Strauss's girl thought Hemingway liked war: "Christ knows I didn't like it for other people." Doesn't understand how people lie about him. "I would rather kill racehorses that I am fond of than lie in a story." Better not to talk and better, in some ways, not to have friends. Can tell what his enemies may do but not his friends. Plans to write stories Strauss will like. Discusses La Condition Humane by Andre Malraux. "Goddamn it takes a while to make a writer." 6250-j
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to [Dick] Armstrong, [1935] December 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:35)
    Thanks for the letter and the clippings. Has been drinking for two months since he got back from New York. Asks Armstrong for a working press pass. Coming down to see fight and to refresh his memory about Cuba. Pauline sends her best. 6250-s
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to [Ralph MacA. Ingersoll], [1939?] May 20, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with typed carbon copy. (Box-folder 3:36)
    Not sore at him but wishes he would come down and fish and discuss set-up. Treated Joe Losey squarely. Hoped Losey could raise money and put on show. Option ran out and Hemingway sold Glazer the right to make adaptation subject to certain conditions. They hoped he would permit his name to be used. Only friendly feeling for Mac and Joe. Never prejudiced their interests. He is under no obligation to ask anyone's advice on how he should dispose of his property, and it was neither disloyal nor unfriendly for him not to come to Mac. 6250-a
  - Papa [Ernest Hemingway] to Patrick and Gregory [Hemingway], [1939] July 14, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:37)
    Hemingway relates story of when he was on the phone and lightning struck throwing him nearly ten feet, of which he could not talk for a long time. "That lightning is powerful. Never try to fool with it." Then next day lightning struck again. Good thing he was wearing dry shoes on the tile floor otherwise he wouldn't be around. Gives good news: they are going to the ranch. Gives details about the logistics of trip to ranch. He is now on page 340 of his book, "but it gets longer and longer all the time." 6250-h
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Cam[pbell Becket], 1945 October 23, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:38)
    Sorry for delayed reply to receipt of notarized papers. Discusses [John H. Hemingway]'s experience in the war, organizing French resistance around Montpellier for the OSS, and his subsequent wounding and capture by the Germans while making a daytime reconnaissance in the Rhone Valley. Working very hard on his new book. Still has a bad headache from the series of concussions he got. He gets his writing done before the headaches start. Did not write Maurice because he is working so hard on the book. 6250-n
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1948 June 27, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:39)
    Discusses stipulations of contract. Asks for length needed, etc. for tear sheets or manuscripts of what their masterminds have written on The Future of Everything. Doesn't know a shit about the future of anything, but will write a good, straight people about what he thinks. Tells of the catch of recent fishing trip. He is down to 210 lbs. Averaged a fish every four minutes. Awfully good life if that is what you like, and that is what he likes. Also, no god-damn photographers. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1948 September 7, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:40)
    Thanks for letter and check. Will try to write the best stories he can. Put off writing due to "general effup" of his attorney and agent, Speiser, etc. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1949 March 9, TLS with autograph postscript, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:41)
    Things quiet in Italy as seven years between elections. Italians are a wonderful people. Probably had worst press in the world. Meeting people he fought against and seeing places with more understanding. Wonderful for him. Owes two stories due by end of December or he returns the dough. Wrote one, but too rough for Cosmopolitan. They've published the best stories he has written. Back to Cuba in May. Life piece made him sick. Difference between Life and life. He tries to be a good character, keeps promises, etc. but doesn't think [Malcolm] Cowley knows anything about what people like him are made of. Reading it, he felt as if he were being formed in Cowley's image. Had a nice, private life before, but now feels like somebody had shit in it and left it there. Glad Truman won, but it has gone to what he thinks of as his head. Mary broke her leg skiing. Raves about Bob Flaherty. Small torn fragment from bottom left of letter in envelope. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1949 June 10, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:42)
    In regard to money advance, will carry it against two short stories rather than the novel, but promises novel to him. Doesn't want to take advance on the novel because he doesn't want anyone looking over his shoulder. All is well. Mary recovered from broken leg. His infection on his face is now better. Kids with us for thirty days. After they leave he will settle down and work. Looking forward to seeing each other, and see Bob Flaherty. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1949 July 8, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:43)
    Glad he liked Holiday piece. Discusses photographers. Mentions Tom Lea's book [The Brave Bulls?], and didn't think it was very good. Hemingway is getting sick of the mystique of bravery etc. being piled on and manufactured situations and crap in general. Glad DiMaggio is playing again. Remembers playing baseball as a youth. Loved it more than any other game. Discusses his relationship with the church: "after being married twice out of the church you would think the Jesuits might have given me up as hopeless." Life is very complicated. Anecdote about chaplain in the 4th Infantry Division. His fighting chickens have won 38 out of 42 fights and keep them in the food. Shooting pigeons. Discusses activities of his sons. Read only one Flaherty profile, which made him seem like a little boy reading it. Hotchner picked a good hero: "We all need one, and I think you got the best one." 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1949 August 22, TLS with autograph postscript, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:44)
    Glad he is coming down in two weeks. Discusses confusion with his expense account when he worked for Mr. Hearst: "The only item I had turned down was the hire of a Felluca. They thought a Felluca had something to do with Felattio (Also mis-spelled) and that I was either over-extending myself or setting up a personal harem." Discusses John O'Hara's books and criticizes him: "He has a pretty ear but he had the terrible inferiority complex of the half-lace curtain Irish and he never learned that it doesn't matter a fuck where you come from, socially, it is where you go." Wrote him off but happy that he was wrong. Mentions his son, Gigi, who threw a pitch at Hemingway's head during baseball game. Discusses Gigi a lot, and states that he is the only boy that "turned out Indian, not Cherokee, Digger, Pyute, Navajo, or any of those unfortunate peoples but Northern Cheyenne and he has all the problems of them, as I always had, and all the lack of problems that having that blood gives you." Has stopped training his chickens because of moulting. Talks of his fishing and their plans when they are together. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1949 September 29, TL with autograph corrections, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:45)
    Gone completely legal and doesn't like the government, and doesn't want to take any favors from them. Wonderful news regarding fight films on the way down. Mary is with her parents and he is lonely. Discusses his activities and amount he is writing. Out to shoot pigeons. Writing is his true love. Drinking is fun, not a release from something. But he is not a first stone caster. Thinks book will run in three installments, and that it is the best one he has written, although he is prejudiced. No doghouse trouble anymore: "A man should know how to get out of that doghouse or else should turn in his suit." But he loves "Miss Mary, truly." Thanks for $10,000 check, but hasn't cashed it yet. Eleven different hurricanes kicking around. "Must get going now or Miss Mary will tell me that I am not taking life seriously. Some day I might take it seriously and a lot of characters would hang by their necks until dead."Signed by Hemingway's secretary, Miss Nita. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1949 October 3, TLS with autograph postscript, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:46)
    Talks about finishing book [Across the River and Into the Trees?]. Will be glad when it's done, but will miss it for a while. Just wrote a "god-damn wonder chapter." Got it all, to break your heart, into two pages. Discusses geographical locations he loves in Western States, such as Red Lodge, Montana or Cody, Wyoming or West Yellowstone or Billings "on a Saturday night" or Casper "where Mary lost our kid." Borrowed 10 G for operation mink coat, for Mary. Went to a circus and saw the lions. Will work the cats in public after the book is done. Would rather work them than do most anything else, if you don't have to use whip, chair, or make theater. Will be introduced as, "An Illustrious domador del norte, now retired from the profession, but who, through his aficion, dedicates this rather special number to the Cuban public." Tells Hotchner it isn't dull where he is. 6250-f
  - Mister Papa [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1949 October 11, TL, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:47)
    Thanks for the fight films. Is at 47,474 words today, which interests the shit out of him. Tells Hotchner that there must be an element of surprise with the book, or there is no deal. Got into trouble with Miss Mary when the photographer showed photographs to them, which included the "whore that we now call Xenophobia." Got into doghouse because of that. Cannot make a lie stick with Miss Mary; it is the quickest way to starve yourself to death that is still available. Will be lonesome when the book is done. He never had a better friend or a more severest critic. Have been slugging it out with Mr. Shakespeare, the writer. I guess maybe he is old. Mentions Mr. Tito who did very well, not for himself, but for everybody. Charlie Scribner is as dumb as a horse. Signed by Hemingway's secretary, Miss Nita. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1949 October 23, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:48)
    Discusses writing. Wants to follow the same system with his new book as he did with For Whom the Bell Tolls. Discusses money possibilities. Explains why he doesn't write letters: "I do not write because I am so God-damned pooped after I write that it is difficult to write letters." Will be leaving for Paris mid November. Use his discretion in cutting of the proof. Sorry fish did not bite. Probably because of the storms, for fish "are as sensitive to the barometer as a woman is to the moon." 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Edward Hotchner, 1949 November 4, D, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:49)
    Telegram. Airmailing first 62 pages and chapter which introduces girl. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ed Hotchner, 1949 November 15, D, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:50)
    Telegram. Will bring all corrected copy except last chapter. Faster than mailing. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed Hotchner, 1949 November 23, D, 2 pages. (Box-folder 3:51)
    Telegram. Urgent. Please call Otto Bruce to see if he can bring car. If not Bruce, ask for Anita Jensen at the American Embassy, Havana. Ask for extension to Buick. Also, in book [Across the River and Into the Trees?] where living generals are called jerks can change to characters. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1950 January 2, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:52)
    Nothing of business to report so make it a personal letter. Everyone misses him. Mary is wonderful. Discusses codes, and includes anecdote about "shelling friendly cruiser." Entered into the Grand Prix pigeon shoot. Only two Americans ever won.
  - Ernest Hemingway to Philip LaFollette, 1950 January 2, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:53)
    Thanks for letter. Didn't know he could write a book as straight as he did and have so many intellectuals hate it. Sorry about the girl being so mature for her age. All stories are made up, but you have to invent from knowledge. American criticism is sort of funny. Anything they have not been taught, they think is not true. If you fight they hate you because they don't fight. Gives anecdote of Col. Jim Luckett. "You write that and they tell you that such things never happened. Finishing up book; it was an attempt to distill. 6250-x
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1950 February 19, TLS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:54)
    Bad timing [about Hotchner being fired]. Does he have any money for coming events and could Hemingway help him? Would not have given the novel to Scribner's except for Hotchner; had promised it to Cosmopolitan and wouldn't let anyone else bid on it. Talks about duck and geese hunting. Dealing with his face infection he had picked up a week ago. Ingrid [Bergman] has "been takeing [sic] her lumps and it did not occur to Rosellini to do anything more chic and gallant than read [Hemingway's] private letters to her to the press." 6250-x
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1950 March 8, TLS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:55)
    Mary broke her leg again, skiing. Tell Ted Patrick that Hotchner controls where Hemingway's stuff goes and that he "would not sell nothing to noplace where [Hotchner] was not working at unless [he] accepted service under the Woman's Home Upfuck or the Ladie's Home Compassion." Mistake to serialize as they did, but they made the mistake and "does a man cry over spilt shit or a spilt horse or whores?" No. Has done the rewrite on the whole book, but wishes Hotchner has been around to help with his "good, clean, smart, just head" and heart as bad as his. 6250-x
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1950 July 4, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:56)
    Apologized for not writing as he has been busy. Recently got a concussion after a fall on the Pilar with a major arterial cut, which was something that "helped a writer the least." It was a very gory story. "Am always bored shitless when am hit or smashed up. Never like to be in bed without a woman or a good book or the Morning Telegraph. " Discusses the ballet with Anne-Marie getting top billing. Sending illustrations to Ted Patrick for The Good Lion and the Faithful Bull. Does not wish to publish The Great Black Horse. Hemingway and Conte [Carlo di] Robilant are heads of a new movement of Venetian writing. Gianfranco Ivancich another member of the Movement. Talks about horse racing. "Never lose your faith in the honesty of sports, boy." 6250-x
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1950 December 7, TLS, 3 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:57)
    Mary [Hemingway] had a piece accepted by Flair. When they fold, they are still committed, aren't they? Discusses accusations of his adultery: "Every time we ever went to the races now rates as triple space adultery." His health is better, although he cannot ride or ski. Can fish and shoot. Going around with heart sort of a displaced person is not much fun but "it is damn sight easier than being in Korea." Has been working with lions: "Takes your mind off things." Has been offered a job working with the cats but decided to stick with book writing. He may do a story on the circus. "The Korean thing takes all the fun out of kidding." His book [Across the River and Into the Trees] best seller for ten weeks. Talks about MacArthur and Sir Charles Willouby, "phony, a passed-over-liar that nobody would take and really a failed Kraut." In regards to the Korean War, "this is the first time my country even fought and I was not there and food has no taste and the hell with love when you can't have children etc." The Post are good people; Collier's have been "bitches, untruthful, and never complying with their obligations." Esquire "like living in a cave with cheap thieves without a sense of humour [sic]." Let him know about CBS deal. Writing more stories. All unpublished in book form. True paying him $2,000 for his sport's stories. Always thinks of Hotchner as his soundest and truest friend. Sorry he caused him any bad luck. 6250-x
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Richard] Stallman, 1951 January 17, negative Photostat, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:58)
    Whether he will be in the States in December, 1951 comes close to being the $64 question. Should not defend his work except with more and better work. Appreciates him defending it if he thinks it good, but he himself should not do so. There wsa great discrepancies between reviews and letters he received regarding last book [Across the River and Into the Trees]. Berenson liked it very much. Many soldiers wrote that they read it four or five times. So far only two wrote against it. Shamus McManus was one. Has to get to work as his head is someplace else. Cannot come to meeting. William B. Seward, in English Department at William and Mary, knows what Hemingway is trying to do. Hemingway couldn't read McCaffery collection. It was "too much writing about something you knew too much about." He "honest to Christ" has to get to work. Believed his last book a fine one and read it over 100 times, but he couldn't say that to people nor make them believe he didn't think it was good because he wrote it. Location of original unknown. 6250-a
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1951 February 7, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:59)